Guide to the Willem J. Kolff audio-visual collection 1949-1995
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Willem J. Kolff audio-visual collection
1949-1995
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0333
Kolff, Willem J., 1912-
16mm films, 8mm films, U-Matic videocassettes, Betacam videocassettes, VHS videocassettes, audiocassettes, microcassettes, reel-to-reel audiotapes, phonograph records and dictaphone cards.
The Willem J. Kolff audio-visual collection (1949-1995) consists of film, video and audio recordings relevant to Kolff's groundbreaking medical research into the development of artificial organs, including the artificial kidney and artificial heart.
Biographical Note
Dr. Willem Johan Kolff (1911-2009) has been an internationally-known name in the world of medicine since 1957 when he began working on the total artificial heart at the Cleveland Clinic in Ohio. Known as the "Father of Artificial Organs", his pioneering spirit actually led him to make giant leaps in medicine long before he was so well-known.
Born February 14, 1911, in Leyden, The Netherlands, Dr. Kolff went to the University of Groningen for his residency in medicine during the German occupation. He started working on the artificial kidney in 1939, and became the first internist at a small hospital in Kampen, where he continued the work on the artificial kidney. The rotating drum kidney was developed in 1941, and by 1955 the twin-coil kidney had led to the possibility of dialysis worldwide. Work on the heart-lung machines began in 1948, and the first membrane oxygenators were used successfully in patients in 1955.
Dr. Kolff and his wife Janke had five children who were all born in the Netherlands. They immigrated to the United States in 1950. Here Dr. Kolff worked in the Research Department and the Department of Surgery of the Cleveland Clinicirca He worked on the artificial kidney, the heart lung machine, and invented the total artificial heart in 1957, one year after becoming a United States citizen. He became Scientific Director of Cleveland's Artificial Organ program, then moved to Utah in 1967 to direct the Division of Artificial Organs and the Institute for Biomedical Engineering at the University of Utah in Salt Lake City.
At the Division of Artificial Organs and the Institute for Biomedical Engineering, Dr. Kolff was in charge of teams working on artificial kidneys, artificial hearing, the artificial eye, artificial arm, the subcutaneous peritoneal access device, and the artificial heart. In 1982 Dr. Barney Clark received the first "permanent artificial heart" implanted in a human. This event made the University of Utah known throughout the world as the leader in artificial organ research.
Dr. Kolff has received more than a hundred awards, among these the prestigious Japan Prize in 1986. He has published more than six hundred articles. He has been active in social issues such as abortion rights and nuclear weapon protests, and has always been interested in nature and art. He died February 11, 2009 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
The Willem J. Kolff audio-visual collection (1949-1995) consists of film, video and audio recordings relevant to Kolff's research into the development of artificial organs, including the artificial kidney and artificial heart. Collection materials show the evolution of Kolff's artificial organs and include experiments, lectures, interviews, patient treatments, etcirca
The materials are arranged roughly chronologically by subject matter. Items detailing Kolff's work on the artificial kidney are followed by those focused on the artificial heart and then by material relevant to the development of other artificial organs and miscellaneous collection materials.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Willem J. Kolff papers (Ms 654) and photograph collection (PO343).
University of Utah--Faculty; University of Utah--Division of Artificial Organs; University of Utah--Institute for Biomedical Engineering; Artificial kidney--Utah--History--Sources; Heart, Artificial--Utah--History--Sources; Heart, Mechanical--Utah--History--Sources; Artificial arms--Utah--History--Sources; Eyes, Artificial--Utah--History--Sources; Medicine and Health; Moving Images; Sound Recordings; Moving images; Sound recordings
- Artificial kidney, 1949-1975
  The items concerned with the artificial kidney date from 1949, the year Kolff introduced the artificial kidney in Kampen, Netherlands, to 1975, as he was developing a wearable artificial kidney. Most of these materials show the evolution of the artificial kidney since 1949, with emphasis on the technical aspect of its use. Other subjects covered include recorded lectures and interviews, visual presentations, patient treatment, peritoneal lavage, single-needle dialysis and transplantation.
  - Artificial kidney, 1949; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 1)
    The gauges of an artificial kidney, the operation of coiled cellophane, connecting a calf with the artificial kidney, and an examination of the calfs kidney. Filmed in Kampen, Netherlands. Ten minutes.
  - Artificial kidney for the treatment of serious uremia, 1949; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 2)
    The construction and use of one of the first artificial kidneys in Kampen, Netherlands. Included are scenes of Kampen, winding cellophane tubing around the artificial kidney drum the addition of salts to the rinsing fluid, and connecting the patient with the artificial kidney. Produced by A. Willering. 10 minutes.
  - Commentary, 1982 November 03; Audiocassette (Cassette 3)
    Narration by Dr. Kolff for item 101. Kolff returns to Kampen, Netherlands and discusses his life's work. See 101 for further details. Nine minutes.
  - Disposable coil kidney, 1956; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 4)
    The manufacturing process and rolling by hand of a twin-coil artificial kidney. 12 minutes.
  - Untitled film, 1958; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 5)
    Two reciprocating air pumps, close oxygenator, poly tank with rinsing fluid, heart suspended in funnel beating. Made by Cahill. Two minutes.
  - Dialysis patient interviews, 1958 April 17; 1958 November 25-27; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 6)
    These interviews were conducted in Cleveland, OH.
    1 Joseph McLoskey, History 854396, age 55, no date given. The interviewer asks the patient about his appetite, physical and mental condition. The patient counts numbers and talks about reading the newspaper.
    2 (Begins at counter 115.) Joanne Sears, History 853475, April 17, 1958. The interviewer asks the patient about her physical and mental condition, appetite, weight, age and walking ability. The patient counts numbers and talks about reading the newspaper.
    3 (Begins at counter 287.) John Milligan, history 832707, November 25, 1958. This interview occurred before the patient's first dialysis, and includes a recording of his respiration. The interviewer asks about his mental and physical condition, age, location of interview, his breathing difficulties and appetite. The patient counts numbers. On November 27, the second day after dialysis, a second interview finds the patient hungry and discussing his pre-dialysis condition. A repeat copy of Milligan's interviews immediately follows, which is more complete than the first. 24 minutes.
  - Dialysis patient interviews, 1959 May 12; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 7)
    Prepared at the Cleveland Clinicirca
    1 Patient Harry Rogers discusses his emotional and physical state.
    2 (Begins at counter 200.) Harry Rogers 24 hours after his first dialysis treatment. He discusses his memory, appetite, hunting, farming, and the alteration in his physical and mental condition. Seven minutes.
  - Dialysis patient interviews, 1958; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 8)
    These interviews are conducted by multiple physicians. They ask the patients about their memory, appetite, physical condition and emotional condition, both immediately after their first, second or third dialysis and a day later.
  - Uremia patient, 1958; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 9)
    Shows patient demonstrating movement skills. Box reads "Patient in uremia; stroke hemiplegia; total renal cortical necrosis." Three minutes.
  - Peritoneal lavage in the rat, July 19; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 10)
    With Calvin Cooper. This shows the weighing of a rat and the procedure of peritoneal lavage, including draining of the fluid and a detail of the abdominal attachment. Four minutes.
  - Film made for The Mike Douglas Show, 1964; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 11)
    Shows working artificial kidney with patients and medical personnel.
    2 minutes.
  - Renal transplantation patients, 1964 January 23; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 12)
    Renal transplant patients demonstrate their recovery by walking and doing light calisthenics on the roof and sun porch (of the Cleveland Clinic?). Five minutes.
  - Coil winding, 1965; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 13)
    This film shows the operation of a winding machine, a patient using an artificial kidney, and the later unwinding of the coil after use.
    Five minutes.
  - Dixon: 1965 Polyneuritis (one year after transplantation), 1955-1966; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 14)
    This film has two segments. The first shows a patient (Dixon?) in a wheelchair demonstrating arm movement and performing simple manual tasks, such as drinking and eating, with a close-up of his hands. The second segment shows the same patient getting out of his wheelchair, standing, and using crutches to walk. Four minutes.
  - Child with nurse, 1965; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 15)
    Two scenes of a child, approximately four to six years of age, in a hospital bed. The first segment shows a nurse in attendance. In the second, the child is recovering from abdominal or chest surgery. The carton reads "Little child playing with a doll and with chest bare showing Teflon coated tubes going into the chest..." Two minutes.
  - McConnor winding machine, 1967; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 16)
    Shows how this winding machine is used to prepare coils for artificial kidney machines. Four minutes.
  - EZS loading, 1970-75; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 17)
    This shows medical personnel wrapping cellophane tubing around layers of boards, after which a patient is connected with the artificial kidney. Five minutes.
  - Single-needle dialysis, 1971; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 18)
    This shows the entire single needle dialysis procedure, including hookup to the machine, the pump, the bubble trap, a bolus of saline entering the bloodline, and disappearing saline in the blood line. The credits list W. J. Kolff and Klaus F. Kopp, M.D. Five minutes.
  - Single-needle dialysis, 1971; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 19)
    This is a slightly different version of item 18.
  - Kidney machine and Dr. Kolff, 1972; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 20)
    Shows Dr. Kolff demonstrating a kidney machine, kidney machine in use with patient, and Kolff at Building 512 at the University of Utah describing the artificial heart.
  - Wearable artificial kidney, 1975; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 21)
    A discussion of progress in the development of a wearable artificial kidney, including a demonstration by Levi Porter and interviews with various unidentified researchers. Reported by Ed Yeates. Two minutes.
  - Dialysis, 1970; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 22)
    1 "The First Dialysis Machine" is narrated by Dr. Kolff. See also items 3, 101.
    2 "Machine Dialysis: A Life Saver" is narrated and directed by Prof. Ed Daub. This film explains dialysis in a technological context, showing its first use in Kampen, Netherlands; the wearable artificial kidney today; arteriovenous shunt and fistula; and advances in dialysis machines. Includes comments from Dr. Weldon Shelp of Methodist Hospital, Madison, WI; nurse Anita Levin, social worker Joan Penrod, and dialysis patients Terry Oberly and Ed Lease. Produced by the Audio Visual Service of the College of Engineering, University of Wisconsin at Madison. 23 minutes.
  - Towards a wearable artificial kidney, 1975; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 23)
    This film, narrated by Dr. Kolff, shows how a wearable artificial kidney could be compatible with the daily life of patients and demonstrates how the machine functions. The credits for the film list W. J. Kolff, M.D., director; S. J. Davidson, Ph. D., 'WAK designer;' E. Thor, M.D.; E Thor, M.D.; E. C. Bullock; D. Vandura; S. Hughes; H. R. Smith and D. Guestaveson. Ten minutes.
  - Wearable artificial kidney, 1975; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 24)
    This film contains unused footage from item 23.
  - Wearable artificial kidney, 1975; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 25)
  - Dr. Kolff speaking on the artificial kidney, 1975 November 04; Audiocassette (Cassette 26)
    1 Brief and incomplete speech on hemodialysis regeneration systems.
    2 Paper, "Towards a Wearable Artificial Kidney", given by Dr. Kolff, using film. Discusses operation of wearable artificial kidney, its components and their manufacture, and the artificial kidney's future.
    3 Dr. Kolff interviews "Kathy," from Ogden, Utah, who uses an artificial kidney.
    4 Dr. Kolff speaks about the benefits of the wearable artificial kidney and the specific case of "Levi," a dialysis patient. 32 minutes.
  - Dialysis symposium, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 27)
    Side A
    Recording of a dialysis symposium (at National Kidney Foundation?) in New York. 32 minutes.
    1 Opening remarks by ?? of the National Institute of Arthritis Metabolism and Digestive Diseases.
    2 Presentation by Dr. Kolff on methods of dialysis and problem of removing urea in dialysis.
    3 Discussion led by Dr. Kolff on improving patient treatment, frequency of dialysis, use of the gastro-intestinal tract for removal of urea.
    Continued on side B.
    Side B
    1 Continuation of discussion on side A, number 3. 12 minutes.
- Artificial heart, 1958-1985
  The items concernde with the artificial heart begin with Kolff's research into artificial heart valves in 1958. Films document the effect of thrombosis on different valve material and high speed photography is used to explore the strengths of different valves, in testing machines. The development of the Norton, or Solenoid, heart is shown in films documenting the insertion of this heart and the recovery of the animals used. Later films present the manufacture and use of a heart made from silasticirca Films made in the early 1960s document progress made in the artificial heart for other researchers, and films made in the 1970s show test animals and other aspects of work on the Jarvik heart at the University of Utah. Completing this section is a videocassette discussing a portable artificial heart driver.
  - Heart valve studies, polyurethane II, 1958; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 28)
    Shows artificial valves with high-speed photography. The label lists "a torn valve, a rigid valve, a good valve, dog valve."
  - Cineangiograms, 1958; 16mm film Silent, black and white and color (Reel 29)
    Cine-cardioangiography studies of a Norton heart in a dog. Six minutes.
  - Short history of monocusp valve, 1959; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 30)
    1 Valve and thrombosis studies.
    2 Patches inside hearts. 3 minutes.
  - Seidel's valve, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 31)
    Shows Seidel's valve on the removed heart of a dog that survived about twenty days, with thrombi on the atrial and ventricular sides. One minute.
  - Seidel's valve (numbers 1, 2 and 3), 1960 August 01; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 32)
    High speed photography of Seidel's valve with chordae tendineae in testing machine, with both straight-on and side views. 5 minutes.
  - Seidel's valve (numbers 4, 5 and 6), 1960 August 01; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 33)
  - Seidel's valve (numbers 7, 8, 9 and 10), 1960 August 01; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 34)
    High speed photography of Seidel's valve with chordae tendineae in testing machine, with both straight-on and side views. 4 minutes.
  - Mitral valve thrombosis, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 35)
    Shows thrombosis on artificial mitral valve of a dog heart. 1 minute.
  - Medicine, 1988-1989; VHS videocassette (Cassette 36)
    This video is narrated in Japanese and was made for ASAHI. It is a tribute to Simon Flexner, an American pathologist, and Hideyo Noguchi, a Japanese bacteriologist who worked together at the Rockfeller University. There is footage from the Cleveland Clinic showing the insertion of an artificial heart in a cow as well as an interview with a medical personnel who discusses both the artificial heart and the artificial kidney. There is also footage of interviews with patients who where waiting for a donated heart followed by an interview with a patient with diabetes who received the second artificial heart implant ever.
  - AV patch thrombosis studies, 30 March 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 37)
    Several segments, including "polyurethane, 7 days." One minute.
  - Valve testing, testing with dogs, and thrombosis, 1958-1961; 16mm film Silent, black and white and color (Reel 38)
    1 Plastic valve in valve-testing machine (circa 1958).
    2 High speed photography of plastic valves.
    3 High speed photography of normal dog valve.
    4 Insertion of tricuspid polyurethane valve in the mitral orifice in a dog (circa 1958).
    5 Defibrillation of the heart.
    6 Similar dog after 35 days.
    7 Angiocardiogram with injection of dye in the laboratory of Sones-Shirey.
    8 Thrombosis on Teflon valves being peeled off (1959).
    9 Norton heart pulsating while being held (1959).
    10 Same heart inserted in a dog.
    11 Following of contrast with image amplifier.
    12 Dog with an air-driven heart inside the chest (1961). 9 minutes.
  - Cine-cardioangiography studies on a dog, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 39)
    Shows studies and the dog recovering from surgery. Norton heart. Six minutes.
  - Pressure graphs, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 40)
    Shows several comparative graphs of ventricular and aortic pressure in a dog's aortic valve and an artificial aortic valve. One minute.
  - Untitled film, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 41)
    Two segments, the first of which is high speed photography of a heart valve, while the second is a cineangiocardiogram of artificial arteries (and heart?). One minute.
  - Heart valve thrombosis studies, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 42)
    1 High-speed photography of artificial valve in operation; peeling away of thrombi from Teflon heart valves, including a monocusp valve.
    2 Angiogram of valve in operation.
    3 Polyurethane monocusp after eight days.
    4 Examination of atrioventricular patch; collagen and atrioventricular patch; Teflon.
    5 Silastic valve after eleven days.
    6 Silastic atrioventricular patch after eight days.
    7 Examination of fibrinolysin and Teflon valves.
    8 Angiograms of valves in operation. 7 minutes.
  - Thrombosis studies, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 43)
    1 Examination of two hearts, one labeled '17 days' and the other labeled 'Dacron collagen.'
    2 Examination of heart labeled '16 days' with Teflon valve. 3 minutes.
  - Teflon mitral heart valves, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 44)
    High speed photography of artificial valves in a testing machine. 10 minutes.
  - Teflon valves, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 45)
    Same as item 44, except this film has numbered sequences. 10 minutes.
  - Valves in testing machine, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white and color (Reel 46)
    1 View of testing machine.
    2 Mitral valve in testing machine.
    3 Mitral valve in heart of dead dog.
    4 Mitral valve. Shows thrombosis after fifteen days.
  - Ball valve, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 47)
    Several segments showing ball valve "instability." Three minutes.
  - Flow studies in prosthetic heart valves, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 48)
    Probably poduced at Cleveland Clinic. National Aeronautics and Space Administration(NASA) high speed photography (500 fps) done at the Lewis Research Center.
    1 Natural aorticirca
    2 Teardrop (mitral).
    3 Cross Jones (aortic).
    4 Trapdoor (aortic).
    5 Starr-Edwards (aortic).
    6 Gott (mitral).
    7 Hammersmith (aortic). 8 minutes.
  - Untitled film, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 49)
    Includes footage of the Bailey oxygenator, the pump of Clark&Gollen, X-rays of dog chests, a diagram of the circulatory system, and dogs at play. Five minutes.
  - Norton heart, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 50)
    Footage of the Norton heart functioning externally and of two dogs with artificial hearts recovering from surgery. Two minutes.
  - Cineangiogram, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 51)
    Cineangiogram of counter pulsation with an intraortic balloon and post-mortem injections into descending aorta with Kolff pump. Five minutes.
  - Post-mortem study: Mr. Hawthorne, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 52)
    Cineangiocardiograms. Two minutes.
  - Angiogram, 1960; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 53)
    Angiogram of a pumping balloon in a patient, post-mortem. Canister label identifies "Mr. Hawthorne." Ten minutes.
  - Atrioventricular captions, 1960; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 54)
    1 "Aortic grafts with rough surfaces are covered with fibrin and stay patent. For valves use knitted Teflon."
    2 "All of the right atrial patches were covered with thrombi. Thrombi were the most extensive 5-9 days after the operation; the largest were on the suture lines."
    3 "Atrioventricular patches were free of thrombi when they had smooth surfaces." Three minutes.
  - Polyurethane tricuspid valve in testing machine, 1961 May; 16mm film Silent, black and white (Reel 55)
    Footage of rubber and polyurthane valves in a testing machine, made by Goodyear, Akron, Ohio. Each valve is identified by a product number and description. 8 minutes.
  - Oxygenator and artificial heart, 1961; 16mm film Silent, color (Reel 56)
    Shows assembly of a membrane oxygenator, an artificial heart operating externally, and a dog with an artificial heart. "This film was shown in Atlantic City at ASAID meeting; Kyestra and Moulopoulos; membrane oxygenator." Three minutes.
  - Intracardiac thrombosis on plastics, 1961; 16mm film Sound, color (Reel 57)
    This film discusses abdominal aortic grafts in dogs; tricuspid mitral Teflon valves and thrombi; atrial patches and thrombi; atrioventricular patches and thrombi; atrioventricular window patches and thrombi; atrioventricular smooth polyurethane patches with Dacron chordae tendineae; selection of chordae tendineae material; construction of and insertion of Seidel's valve; and conclusions on how to avoid thrombosis on artificial valves. This film was made with V. Mirkovitch, M. D.; T. Akutu, M. D.; and W. Seidel, M. D. and was produced by the Cleveland Clinic, Department of Artificial organs. It is narrated by Dr. Kolff.
  - Dog barking, 1961 March 10; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 58)
    Prepared at Cleveland Clinicirca This is a recording of a dog with a belloframe artificial heart barking, the sound of the air pump, and the sound of the artificial heart valves. Drs. Akutsu, Merkowitz and Seidel performed the operation. Six minutes.